William Edmund Curtis Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
William Edmund Curtis Papers 1885-1923 1893-1896
MSS17491
Curtis, William Edmund, 1855-1923
2,000 items
11 containers
2.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Assistant secretary of the United States Treasury. Family and general correspondence, financial papers, memoranda, notes, reports, codebooks, invitations, scrapbooks, newspaper clippings, printed matter, and other material relating chiefly to Curtis's service as assistant secretary of the treasury.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Adee, Alvey A. (Alvey Augustus), 1842-1924--Correspondence.; Carlisle, John Griffin, 1835-1910--Correspondence.; Crawford, F. Marion (Francis Marion), 1854-1909--Correspondence.; Curtis, William Edmund, 1855-1923.; Fairchild, Charles S. (Charles Stebbins), 1842-1924--Correspondence.; Field, Hickson W. (Hickson Woolman), 1823- --Correspondence.; Gilder, Richard Watson, 1844-1909--Correspondence.; Goschen, Edward, Sir, 1847-1924--Correspondence.; Gough, Hugh Henry, Sir, 1833-1909--Correspondence.; Johnstone, Alan, Sir--Correspondence.; Jordan, C. N. (Conrad N.), 1830-1903--Correspondence.; McCoy, Joseph S.--Correspondence.; Muhleman, Maurice L. (Maurice Louis), 1852-1913--Correspondence.; Peffer, William Alfred, 1831-1912--Correspondence.; Rosengarten, J. G. (Joseph George), 1835-1921--Correspondence.; Speyer, James, 1861-1941--Correspondence.; Stillman, James, 1850-1918--Correspondence.
Organizations
United States. Department of the Treasury.
Subjects
Customs administration--United States.; Deficit financing--United States.; Gold standard.; Government lending--United States.; Inflation (Finance)--United States.; Silver question.
Places
United States--Economic policy.
Occupations
Public officials.
Acquisition Information
The papers of William Edmund Curtis, assistant secretary of the treasury, were given to the Library of Congress by Curtis in 1902. Additional papers were given by his sister, Elizabeth Curtis, in 1929.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of William Edmund Curtis are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of William Edmund Curtis (1855-1923) span the years 1885-1923, with the bulk of the material dated 1893-1896. The papers include family and general correspondence, financial papers, memoranda, notes, reports, code books, invitations, a biographical sketch, scrapbooks, newspaper clippings, and printed matter.
The collection relates chiefly to Curtis's service as assistant secretary of the United States Treasury and covers financial topics relating to silver certificates, gold reserves, deficit spending, loans, custom receipts, and inflation. The papers also include letters from Curtis to his mother, Mary Ann Scovill Curtis, chronicling his day-to-day activities.
Correspondents include Alvey A. Adee, John Griffin Carlisle, F. Marion Crawford, Charles S. Fairchild, Hickson W. Field, Richard Watson Gilder, Sir Edward Goschen, Sir Hugh Henry Gough, Sir Alan Johnstone, C. N. Jordan, Joseph S. McCoy, Maurice L. Muhleman, William Alfred Peffer, J. G. Rosengarten, James Speyer, and James Stillman.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material and therein chronologically.
Container List
- Correspondence and other papers (Box 1)
  - 1885, Mar. 1-1893, Oct. 5 (Box 1)
  - 1893, Oct. 6-1894, Feb. 3 (Box 2)
  - 1894, Feb. 5-Sept. 5 (Box 3)
  - 1894, Sept. 6-1895, Jan. 25 (Box 4)
  - 1895, Jan. 28-June 26 (Box 5)
  - 1895, July 1-1896, Jan. 16 (Box 6)
  - 1896, Jan. 17-Sept. 5 (Box 7)
  - 1896, Sept. 7-1908, Sept. 8 (Box 8)
  - Undated (Box 9)
- Miscellany (Box 10)
  - Biographical sketch, 1923 (Box 10)
  - Clippings, 1894-1897 (Box 10)
  - Codebooks, 1895 (Box 10)
  - Fragments, 1896, undated (Box 10)
  - Printed matter, 1885, 1893-1899, undated, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Scrapbooks, 1893-1910, undated, (2 vols.) (Box 11)